I'm going to run each piece of example code and see what it does.
我要运行每一个示例代码 以了解它们的用途
The first piece of code involves adding a series to a square data frame.
第一个代码是用于 Series 和方形 DataFrame 之间的加法
That is, a data frame with the same number of rows as columns.
方形 DataFrame 是行与列数量相等的 DataFrame
I've used 0, 1, 2, and 3 as both the index values and the column names here.
我把索引值和列名均设为 0、1、2 和 3
I've printed out both the original data frame, and
为了方便比较
the result of adding the series here for comparison.
我把原 DataFrame 和添加 Series 后的结果都打了出来
It looks like the value 1 was added to each value in the first column,
可以看到 第一列的每个值都加了 1
2 was added to each value in the second column, and so on.
第二列的每个值都加了 2 以此类推
So it looks like each value from the series was added to one of
看起来 Series 的每个值好像都与
the columns of the dataframe.
DataFrame 各列相加了
Given this, I have an idea what will happen if I add a series to a dataframe
看到这里 我大概知道了
with a single row.
DataFrame 单行与 Series 相加的结果
But I'll try it anyway.
但我还是要试验一下
Again, I've printed both data frames here for comparison, and
同样地 为方便比较 我打出了两个 DataFrame
again it looks like each value from the series was added to a single column
与之前一样 Series 的每一个值好像
from the data frame.
都与 DataFrame 的每一列相加了
1 was added to the first column, 2 was added to the second column and so on.
第一列的每个值都加了 1 第二列的每个值都加了 2 以此类推
Something that might not be obvious given this is what will happen if I add
不太明显的一点是
a series to a data frame with only one column?
如果我把 Series 与仅有一列的 DataFrame 相加 会怎么样呢？
Will it figure out somehow that it should add the values to
它会自动将每个值
each row of the data frame instead?
与 DataFrame 的每一行相加吗？
I tried it out here, and you can see that's not what happened.
我试了一下 可以看到 结果并非如此
Instead, the result of the addition actually has four columns, one for
事实上 相加后的结果有四列
each value in the series, and every column except the first contains NaNs.
每一列对应 Series 的一个值 而除第一列外的其它列都含有 NaN
The first column had 1 added to each value, as before.
与之前一样 第一列的每个值都加了 1
By the way, the code df.add s it's usually the same as df plus s,
顺便说一下 代码 df.add(s) 通常与 df+s 相同
so I usually don't call this function.
所以 我一般不调用这个函数
But the benefit of using this function is that it can also take
但使用这个函数的好处在于
an axis argument.
你还可以使用数轴参数
If I use axix = columns, I get the same result as df plus s.
如果我设数轴等于列 那么所得结果与 df+s 的相同
However if I use axis='index' then each value of the series will be added to
但如果我设数轴等于索引值 那么
one row of the data frame, which might be what I want in some cases.
Series 的每一个值会与 DataFrame 的各行相加 有时 这可能是我们需要的
Now in all the examples I've tried so far, the index of the series has been
在我试验的所有示例中
the same as the column names of the data frame, 0, 1, 2, and 3.
Series 的索引值均与 DataFrame 的列名相同 即 0、1、2、3
Now I'm going to look at an example where that's not the case.
现在我要试一个不同情况的例子
Here the index of the series is B,C, D, and E and
这里的 Series 索引值为 B、C、D、E
the column name of the data frame are A, B, C, and D.
而 DataFrame 的列名则是 a、b、c、d
The result here is very similar to what happened when we added Pandas series and
结果与我们把 pandasSeries 相加时的结果十分相似
the indexes didn't match exactly.
这里的索引值并不匹配
For each letter that wasn't present in both the data frame and
对于不同时存在于 DataFrame 和 Series 的字母
the series, the result is NaN.
其结果为 NaN
For letters that were present in both,
对于两者均拥有的字母
the addition has been matched up based on letter.
其相加结果是根据字母匹配的
So every value in the b column has had 1 added to it and
所以 b 列的每一个值都加了 1
1 was the value in the series with index b.
而 1 正是 Series 中索引 b 的值
So in summary, adding a data frame to a series,
总体来说 将 DataFrame 和 Series 相加
adds each value of the series to one column of the data frame.
就是将 DataFrame 的每一列与 Series 的每一个值相加
And it matches up the series to the dataframe using the index of the series
它根据 Series 的索引值和 DataFrame 的列名
and the column names of the dataframe.
匹配 Series 和 DataFrame